[
  {
    "question": "Why is price elasticity of demand negative?",
    "a": "market inefficiency",
    "b": "the law of demand",
    "c": "diminishing returns to scale",
    "d": "imperfect competition",
    "e": "opportunity costs",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What relationship does price elasticity of demand indicate?",
    "a": "how much consumers are willing to pay on the margin",
    "b": "how much utility consumers obtain from the next unit",
    "c": "how marginal returns diminish with scale",
    "d": "how much consumer surplus increases per unit",
    "e": "how sensitive consumers are to price changes",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following situations is supply relatively inelastic?",
    "a": "A 3% change in price leads to a 2.5% change in supply.",
    "b": "A 3% change in price leads to a 3% change in supply.",
    "c": "A 3% change in price leads to unlimited change in supply.",
    "d": "A 3% change in price leads to a 4% change in supply.",
    "e": "A 3% change in price leads to no change in supply.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "For what MAIN reason do gold coins have an inelastic supply?",
    "a": "Sellers face barriers to entry.",
    "b": "The inputs are scarce.",
    "c": "They are a luxury good.",
    "d": "The good is hard to transport.",
    "e": "The market is imperfectly competitive.",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which economic concept is calculated with the formula (Q∆P)/(P∆Q)?",
    "a": "opportunity cost",
    "b": "comparative advantage",
    "c": "diminishing returns",
    "d": "GDP per capita",
    "e": "elasticity",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following goods has the LOWEST elasticity of demand?",
    "a": "insulin",
    "b": "cars",
    "c": "milk",
    "d": "toilet paper",
    "e": "gasoline",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following goods has the MOST elastic supply curve?",
    "a": "cut diamonds",
    "b": "underground bunkers",
    "c": "sixteenth-century art",
    "d": "artisan sandwiches",
    "e": "vacation yachts",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "For what factor is price elasticity of supply a proxy?",
    "a": "how easily suppliers can change their prices",
    "b": "the opportunity cost of supplying the good",
    "c": "how much price can change without affecting quantity demanded",
    "d": "how much profit suppliers make",
    "e": "how easily suppliers can change their output",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors does NOT affect price elasticity of demand?",
    "a": "substitutes for the good",
    "b": "time horizon",
    "c": "market definition of the good",
    "d": "scarce resources",
    "e": "necessity of the good",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena does NOT explain long-run elasticity?",
    "a": "Suppliers need to adjust to different profits.",
    "b": "Suppliers hire more employees.",
    "c": "Suppliers need to train workers.",
    "d": "Suppliers use up more raw materials.",
    "e": "Suppliers require more tools.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the price elasticity of supply for Picasso paintings?",
    "a": "inelastic",
    "b": "unit elastic",
    "c": "perfectly inelastic",
    "d": "elastic",
    "e": "perfectly elastic",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "When price rises from $20 to $40, the quantity demanded falls from 12,400 to 6,200. Demand is",
    "a": "elastic",
    "b": "perfectly elastic",
    "c": "inelastic",
    "d": "perfectly inelastic",
    "e": "unit elastic",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following products likely has the MOST elastic demand?",
    "a": "Coke",
    "b": "soft drinks",
    "c": "gasoline",
    "d": "Bernini sculptures",
    "e": "milk",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following slopes corresponds to the LEAST elastic supply curve?",
    "a": "10",
    "b": "1/2",
    "c": "1",
    "d": "2",
    "e": "5",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 25% change in the price of gasoline results in an 50% change in the supply of gasoline. What is the price elasticity of supply?",
    "a": "-2",
    "b": "-1/2",
    "c": "2",
    "d": "25",
    "e": "1/2",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Price ceilings do NOT result in a(n)",
    "a": "lower equilibrium price",
    "b": "reduction in total surplus",
    "c": "inefficient outcome",
    "d": "reduction in producer surplus",
    "e": "higher quantity supplied",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following terms refers to a form of price control?",
    "a": "anti-trust laws",
    "b": "minimum wage",
    "c": "logrolling",
    "d": "patent laws",
    "e": "income taxes",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does a price floor appear on a supply and demand diagram?",
    "a": "vertically to the right of the equilibrium point",
    "b": "vertically at the equilibrium point",
    "c": "horizontally above the equilibrium point",
    "d": "horizontally at the equilibrium point",
    "e": "parallel to the demand curve shifted to the right",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of the following goods will a tax generate the MOST revenue?",
    "a": "gasoline",
    "b": "insulin",
    "c": "cars",
    "d": "cigarettes",
    "e": "soda",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answer choices would be reduced as a result of deadweight loss?",
    "a": "producer surplus",
    "b": "barriers to entry",
    "c": "tax revenue",
    "d": "social welfare",
    "e": "consumer savings",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answer choices BEST describes the effects of taxes on supply and demand?",
    "a": "overconsumption, transfer of revenue to suppliers",
    "b": "deadweight loss, government revenue",
    "c": "deadweight loss, transfer of revenue to consumers",
    "d": "overconsumption, goods shortages",
    "e": "imposition of barriers to entry, deadweight loss",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elasticities describes the market with LEAST deadweight loss from taxes? Assume the first value is elasticity of demand and the second value is elasticity of supply.",
    "a": "-.5, .5",
    "b": "-1.5, 1.5",
    "c": "-1, 1.5",
    "d": "-1, 1",
    "e": "-1.5, 1",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What outcome MUST result from price controls?",
    "a": "movement toward equilibrium",
    "b": "deadweight loss",
    "c": "decreased consumer surplus",
    "d": "increased total surplus",
    "e": "positive externalities",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "After which of the following events is a price ceiling MOST likely to be imposed?",
    "a": "drastic increase in apartment prices",
    "b": "overconsumption of cigarettes",
    "c": "farmers lobbying for higher prices",
    "d": "under-consumption of honey",
    "e": "over-pollution of the environment",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What change likely occurs in a market after a price ceiling is imposed?",
    "a": "lower-quality products",
    "b": "increased entrants to the market",
    "c": "increased price competition",
    "d": "higher supply",
    "e": "lower demand",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the supply curve shift if a $1 tax is placed on suppliers?",
    "a": "It shifts diagonally by $1.",
    "b": "It shifts rightward by $1.",
    "c": "It shifts downwards by $1.",
    "d": "It does not shift.",
    "e": "It shifts leftwards by $1.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following markets would be MOST impacted by a social welfare tax?",
    "a": "rare art",
    "b": "milk",
    "c": "diamonds",
    "d": "insulin",
    "e": "jam",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What MAIN factor determines the distribution of tax burdens?",
    "a": "total supply",
    "b": "elasticity",
    "c": "externalities",
    "d": "rivalry",
    "e": "total demand",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements MOST likely describes a market with a rent ceiling of $500/month?",
    "a": "Rent has been increasing.",
    "b": "There are more landlords than renters.",
    "c": "The government taxes rental income.",
    "d": "Alternative rental markets have emerged.",
    "e": "Renters will discriminate against certain tenants.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What MAIN factor drove the 1979 changes in United States oil prices?",
    "a": "reduction in complements",
    "b": "reduced supply",
    "c": "higher demand",
    "d": "government taxation",
    "e": "emergence of substitutes",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  }
]

